בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is קט"ז, Kof Tet Zayin,
116, and we pick up at the bottom of קט"ו עמוד ב'.
Kof Tet Vav Amud Bet. To quickly review what we've said so
far, again I have your sheet here of the distilled version of
the הגדה. Hagada. We did קידוש. Kiddush. ורחץ, Urchatz, the גמרא Gemara
introduced this idea, it was not in the משנה, Mishna, took for
granted that you wash your hands and you wash it twice, said
it was because of the dipping of the כרפס karpos in the
liquid.
Question about, you know, whether that's a general requirement? Is it because
you'll make yourself טמא, tamei, you'll make the food טמא? tamei? Do
you make a ברכה bracha or not? But we don't make a
ברכה. bracha. רמב"ם Rambam has a ברכה. bracha. Do we do it
other times we have wet food? Then כרפס, karpos, which in the
משנה Mishna was מרור. maror. The
גמרא Gemara made it sound like, it was clear it was an
exception because there was not another vegetable available, which is a little
strange that there wasn't another vegetable available. Actually makes it go, you
know, later in the גמרא Gemara it sounds like some people maybe
didn't care, were willing to have מרור maror even if there was
other alternatives.
And maybe as I suggested, you know, maybe דוקא dafka there's an
idea of having מרור maror up front. It fits in with the
fact that one of the four questions is going to be about
the מרור maror before the מרור maror has occurred and the whole
symbolism of the מרור maror begins at the beginning of the סדר.
Seder. Nevertheless, because of questions of when you make על אכילת מרור,
Al Achilat Maror, if you do מרור maror in the front and
later, the, you know, the practice developed that you use other vegetables
here. So that's the כרפס. karpos. We discussed how much of it
you eat, the idea of the אשכנזים Ashkenazim that you don't eat
less than a כזית kezayit in order, in order
so you don't have to do a ברכה אחרונה bracha achrona because
as the גמרא Gemara speaks about the fact that the הגדה Hagada
is a הפסק. hefsek. So to get out of that question of
is it a הפסק, hefsek, is it not? Whatever, do you יוצא
yotzei with ברכת המזון? Birkat Hamazon? Do you need a ברכה אחרונה?
bracha achrona? We eat less than a כזית. kezayit. The רמב"ם Rambam
says you דוקא dafka eat a כזית kezayit because there's an obligation
to do אכילה. achila. And I pointed out that makes a nice
way that you could get some food into you before the סדר
Seder gets really underway.
Again, what do you dip it in?
The גמרא Gemara doesn't say. The רמב"ם Rambam understands that you dip
it in חרוסת. charoset. Again, חרוסת charoset symbolism of the slavery, important
to have that up front. חרוסת charoset normally goes with the מרור.
maror. And if the מרור maror was a major thing that you
used for כרפס, karpos, then also we understand why that's the case.
תוספות Tosafot and others, although some אשכנזים Ashkenazim said the same as
רמב"ם. Rambam. Others say that it's not something else, other than that
salt water, vinegar, whatnot. And then the question is, do you eat
with הסיבה haseiba or without הסיבה? haseiba? Again, the more it's a
symbolism of the slavery and the more this started with an idea
of מרור, maror, then you're going to eat it without הסיבה. haseiba.
If it's a type of a, of a way the Romans eat
with dipping before the meal, then you would eat it with הסיבה.
haseiba. That is an issue that is debated. So those are the
primary components that we have seen until now. We also discussed how
we got to the idea of כורך korech and why we do
first מצה, matzah, then מרור, maror, then כורך, korech, because you can't
have things that are at different levels mixed together. So the last
thing we discussed was the removing of the plate, which was not
clear, although our משנה Mishna in the משנה, Mishna, although our משנה
Mishna did say, first it says they brought before him the thing
that he's going to do the dipping, and then it says they
brought before him the מצה, matzah, חזרת, chazeret, and חרוסת. charoset. So
what is this second bringing? So the גמרא Gemara talks about the
fact that they would remove the plate in order that the תינוקות
tinokos would notice. So if we take a look, I want to
look quickly at the רשב"ם Rashbam at the bottom of קט"ו עמוד
ב'. Kof Tet Vav Amud Bet. ואין עוקר את השולחן, Ve'ein oker
et hashulchan, he says, the last, the last of the medium-sized lines,
מצוה היא לעקור את השולחן קודם הגדה, Mitzvah hi la'akor et hashulchan
kodem l'Hagada, כי היכי דלהוי היכר לתינוקות, Ki heichi d'lehavay heker l'tinokos,
that there should be something there to stimulate the interest of the
children. והני מילי לדידהו דהוה להו שולחן קטן, Ve'hanei milei ledidhu d'hava
lehu shulchan katan, they had a small table with, and it's like
a little, a little what do you call it, like a tray,
לפניהם בשעת הגדה לבדה. lifneihem besha'at Hagada levada. וכן לכל אחד. Ve'chen
l'chol echad. אבל אנו מסלקין את הקערה, Aval anu mesalkin et hake'ara,
we remove not the table but the plate, שבה מצה ומרור ושני
תבשילין, sheba matzah u'maror u'shnei tafshilin, right, the קערה, ke'ara, the סדר
Seder plate, לסוף השולחן. l'sof hashulchan. We take it off to the
side of the table, the end of the table. ודי לנו בכך.
V'dai lanu be'kach. Now interesting. ויש שנוהגים להגביה את הקערה על הכתף
V'yesh shenohagim l'hagbi'ah et hake'ara al hakatef and
מוציאים את הפת מן הקערה. motzi'im et hapat min hake'ara. Okay, so
some would put it on the shoulder. And you might be aware
that there's some that have a מנהג minhag at the beginning to
put the מצה matzah on their backs and say, this is what
our forefathers did when they left מצרים. Mitzrayim. Although it's a little
funny, because remember that doing that is a re-enacting of the גאולה,
Geula, and at this stage presumably we're focused still on the שעבוד
shibbud and on the עבדה. avda. Anyway, and then he discusses taking
off the meat, and that's going to tie into a discussion later
about lifting up the meat and is the meat symbolizing the פסח
Pesach or not? But anyway, what I wanted you to see
is the idea of lifting up, which some have the practice with
the מצה. matzah. So if you go three lines to the bottom
of the רשב"ם, Rashbam, he says, אין צריך להוציא ממנה התבשיל וגם
הגבהה חנם. Ein tzarich l'hotzi mimena hatavshil v'gam hagbahah chinam. There's no
need to do this lifting up. ואין כאן היכר לתינוק. V'ein kan
heker letinok. אבל עוקר הקערה לגמרי ומניחה בקרן זווית, Aval oker hake'ara
legamrei u'manicha bekeren zavit, כאילו כבר אכלו, ke'ilu kvar achlu, כדי שישאלו.
k'dei sheyish'alu. שיכיר התינוק וישאל ודמי לאקצורי שולחן. she-yakir ha-tinok v'yishal v'dami
l'aktzorei shulchan. I think it's more of a היכר heker if you
start carrying a plate on your shoulders, but okay, anyway, he says
the basic point
is you remove it, "hey, why'd we finish?", and then you bring
it back. So this idea of עקירת הקערה, akirat ha-ke'arah, not the
covering of the מצות, matzot, but the actual removal of the plate,
if you notice again at the instructions here I handed out, right
after you say הא לחמא עניא Ha Lachma Anya at the beginning
of מגיד, Maggid, מסיר את הקערה מעל השולחן. masir et ha-ke'arah mei-al
ha-shulchan. I don't know how many people are מקפיד makpid about doing
this, you know, maybe moving it a little bit aside, actually removing
it from the table, you know, I don't think many people are
that מקפיד makpid on this. It's interesting because this is something that
really is in the גמרא Gemara about עוקרים את השולחן, okrim et
ha-shulchan, and then you have, "oh, what's going on, you're removing it",
so then that's where you put in the מה נשתנה. Mah Nishtanah.
מוזגים כוס שני וכאן הבן שואל מה נשתנה, mozgin kos sheni v'kan
ha-ben sho'el Mah Nishtanah, and then, "oh, you ask מה נשתנה, Mah
Nishtanah, good", now we got you, we stimulated your interest, and then
מחזירין את הקערה על השולחן. machzirin et ha-ke'arah al ha-shulchan. So that
is exactly what the גמרא Gemara discussed just here, and we placed
it right before the מה נשתנה, Mah Nishtanah, which as the גמרא
Gemara says that when they did this, אביי Abaye was in front
of רבה Rabbah and he says, "hey, what's going on, why did
you remove the קערה?". ke'arah? He says, "good, now we don't have
to say מה נשתנה". Mah Nishtanah And that's something we're going to
see in a minute too, which is, it sounds literally like as
long as you're asking something we can skip מה נשתנה. Mah Nishtanah.
מה נשתנה Mah Nishtanah is if you're not asking yourself, but תוספות
Tosafot doesn't like not doing the actual formal the whole the whole
text. So תוספות Tosafot says no, first you ask about the שולחן
shulchan and then you follow it with the מה נשתנה. Mah Nishtanah.
Of course, what that means you exempt us if you actually said
it, I don't know. Anyway, but that's exactly the removing, the מה
נשתנה, Mah Nishtanah, asking questions, and then the bringing back. Now we
move on, let's go back to יחץ. Yachatz. So let's take a
look now four lines from the bottom.
Yeah? Short question, so if you do like the רמב"ם Rambam suggests
or says and you have a כזית kezayit of בורא פרי האדמה
Borei Pri HaAdama and you dip in חרוסת charoset and in some
מרור, maror, what ברכה אחרונה berachah acharonah are you making? בורא נפשות?
Borei Nefashot? Yeah, בורא נפשות. Borei Nefashot. Yep, yep. Okay, אמר שמואל,
Amar Shmuel, says שמואל, Shmuel, לחם עוני, Lechem Oni, whatever it says,
לחם עוני. Lechem Oni. What does that mean? Poor person or bread
of affliction? לחם שעונים עליו דברים הרבה, lechem she-onim alav devarim harbeh,
a bread that you say over it many things, that you talk
about it and you talk about the story in relationship to the
bread and we're going to see later today there's other פסוקים. pesukim.
בעבור זה עשה ה' לי בצאתי ממצרים, ba'avur zeh asah Hashem li
b'tzeiti mi-Mitzrayim, as we say in the הגדה.
Haggadah. בעבור זה לא אמרתי אלא בשעה שיש מצה ומרור מונחים לפניך.
ba'avur zeh lo amarti ela b'sha'at she-yesh matzah u-maror munachim l'fanecha.
So this is the importance of not just eating certain foods and
telling the story, but tying the story into the foods and the
symbols that you are doing. So לחם שעונים עליו דברים הרבה. lechem
she-onim alav devarim harbeh. The הגדה Haggadah is said over the מצה,
matzah, and this is why the מצה matzah is exposed during the
telling of the הגדה, Haggadah, the הגדה Haggadah is in reference to
the מצה matzah and therefore that is the symbol that's integrated and
used in the telling of the story. עונים, onim,
literally like as a responsiveness, it could be and it's reflecting the
issue about the בן שואל ben sho'el and you are עונה, oneh,
and that's a very good point. I mean עונים onim could just
mean to proclaim, but it could really mean to
answer. וענית ואמרת לפני ה'
אלהיך,
v'anita v'amarta lifnei
Hashem Elokecha, but you are correct, I actually, you know, that the
whole point that the child asks, right, מה נשתנה Mah Nishtanah and
then you respond, right? So right, if you take a look actually
at the instructions we just had, מחזירין את הקערה, machzirin et ha-ke'arah,
המצות יהיו מגולות בשעת אמירת ההגדה ha-matzot yihyu megulot b'sha'at amirat ha-Haggadah
and then you start responding עבדים היינו. Avadim Hayinu. So in a
way it's a good point, the עונה oneh is here also in
response to the questions of the child. לחם שעונים עליו דברים הרבה,
lechem she-onim alav devarim harbeh,
so I assume proclaim, but I take the point it could very
much also mean respond. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, ואית דאמרי,
v'it d'amri, לחם עוני, Lechem Oni, לחם שעונים עליו דברים הרבה. lechem
she-onim alav devarim harbeh. דבר אחר, Davar acher,
לחם עוני, Lechem Oni, עני ani כתיב, ketiv, written without the ו.
vav. מה עני שדרכו בפרוסה, mah ani she-darko bifrusah, the same way
a poor person doesn't have a whole loaf, only has a partial
loaf, אף כאן בפרוסה, af kan bifrusah, when you tell the story
of the הגדה Haggadah it should represent bread of a poor person
and bread of affliction which is why it is not a whole
loaf, okay, which is יחץ. Yachatz. Now we know where you get
יחץ Yachatz from. Why do you have יחץ Yachatz right before מגיד?
Maggid? Because מגיד Maggid is said over the bread, over the לחם
עוני. Lechem Oni. לחם עוני Lechem Oni represents at this stage bread
of affliction and therefore it's not a whole loaf and that's why
you do יחץ. Yachatz. Okay, the idea of do you then hide
it and get the kids interest, we heard the idea before חוטפין
מצה, chotfin matzah, but the basic reason you have יחץ Yachatz here
is in order to get this symbolism of לחם עוני Lechem Oni
and the לחם עוני Lechem Oni right before מגיד. Maggid. דבר אחר,
Davar acher, another explanation. מה דרכו של עני הוא מסיק ואשתו אופה,
mah darko she-ani hu masik v'ishto ofah, the same way a poor
person you can't waste any fuel so he is getting the lighting
the fire and getting the fire burning and his wife is kneading
the dough and they're getting it into the fire as soon as
the fire is lit cause you have no fuel to waste, אף
כאן נמי הוא מסיק ואשתו אופה. af kan nami hu masik v'ishto
ofah. Similar when you make מצה matzah you have to be very,
you
know, industrious, right, but also like, you know...
efficient, thank you, right, so that you are not wasting any time
so you don't want to let it become חמץ chametz *chametz*. Now
the idea here of בפרוסה *b'prusa* in addition to introducing the idea
of יחץ yachatz. *yachatz* raises the question about whether you make המוציא
*hamotzi* on a broken loaf of bread? Do you need two whole
loaves? And there's a major debate in general whether you need two
loaves for יום טוב *yom tov*, because usually we have two loaves
is because a double loaf fell on שבת shabbos *shabbos*, but on
ערב יום טוב *erev yom tov* if you think about it, A,
the תורה Torah *torah* doesn't say it, B, there's really not a
need for two loaves. Number one, you're allowed to carry on יום
טוב *yom tov*. Number two, you're allowed to prepare food on יום
טוב *yom tov*. Okay, so now do you need in general two
loaves? If you do need two loaves, then can one of them
be broken? So there's a debate in the ראשונים rishonim *rishonim*. Most
ראשונים rishonim *rishonim* assume, the רי"ף *Rif* and others, that you need
two loaves, but some say, but because of the idea of דרכו
של עני בפרוסה *darko shel ani b'prusa* for ליל סדר leil seder,
*leil seder*, one of the loaves is allowed to, not allowed to,
should be broken. That, you know, the whole loaf becomes a partial
loaf because that's the nature of it at ליל סדר leil seder
*leil seder*. Yes, others, like תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos*, says that you have
three, two שלמים *shleimim*, שלמות *shleimot*, and one broken, the broken because
of the לחם עוני *lechem oni*, the שלמות *shleimot* because you require
two whole loaves on a יום טוב *yom tov* meal. Okay, and
that's our practice although some actually do the one and a half.
So if you take a look at תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos*, let's look
quickly, מר דרכו של עני בפרוסה *mar darko shel ani b'prusa*. So
it says תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos*,
he says like this: I will do from the beginning, נראה דגם
המוציא צריך לברך על הפרוסה וכן מבאר כיצד מברכים הכל מודים בפסח
שמניח פרוסה
בתוך שלמה
*nira d'gam hamotzi tzarich l'varech al haprusa v'chein mavaer
keitzad mevorchim hakol modim b'pesach shemaniach prusa
b'toch shleima*. And then it says, okay, one
minute. Okay, so it's a line such as toward שב *shav*, so
שצריך שם מצה matzah שלישית משום לחם משנה mishna. *shetzarich sham matzah
shlishis mishum lechem mishneh* and ten lines down in the narrow line
וחייב לבצוע על שתי ככרות בין בשבת בין ביום טוב *v'chayav livtzoa
al shtei kikarot bein b'shabbos bein b'yomtov*. Okay, and then he says
וכן פסק רב Rav אלפס שצריך לבצוע על שתי ככרות ביום טוב
*v'chein pasak Rav Alfas shetzarich livtzoa al shtei kikarot b'yom tov*, but
the רי"ף *Rif* says that one of them should be a half
on ליל סדר Lyl Seder. *leil seder*. והטעם לפי שהיה לחם משנה
mishna. יורד בערבי ימים טובים *v'hataam lefi shehaya lechem mishneh yored b'arvei
yamim tovim*. Okay, but that's a problem, וקשיא שאנו מתפללים ואתה קדשתנו
וברכתנו מכל הימים קדשתנו מכל הזמנים ואמר במן ברכה bracha במן קדשתא
אף במצה יום טוב היה מן יורד *v'kashya she'anu mispallelim v'attah kidashtanu
v'berachtanu mikol hayamim kidashtanu mikol hazmanim v'amar baman beracha baman kidashta af
b'matzo yom tov haya man yored*. So there's a question whether we
anyway need two loaves, whether there was מן *man* on יום טוב
*yom tov* or not. And then he says, but he says you
have the two whole loaves plus the half. וכן היה נוהג הרב
מנחם מיוני והרב יום טוב שהיו מברכים הכל על הפרוסה *v'chein haya
noheg haRav Menachem miYoni v'haRav Yom Tov shehayu mevorchim hakol al haprusa*.
So they would have two loaves but the ברכה bracha *bracha*, I
don't know what it means to be מברך על *mevorech al*, their
כוונה *kavana* I guess would be that the המוציא *hamotzi* and the
על אכילת מצה achilas matzah, *al achilat matzah* would be on the
פרוסה *prusa*. אך ר"י היה מברך המוציא על השלמה והדר על אכילת
מצה matzah. על הפרוסה ובוצע משניהם יחד *ach Ri haya mevorech hamotzi
al hashleima v'hadar al achilat matzah al haprusa
uvotzeia mi'shneihem yachad*, which is what we do. I mean, again, it's
all just a question of כוונה *kavana*. You know, you hold all
three together, you say המוציא *hamotzi* and then you drop the bottom
one and then you say על אכילת מצה matzah, *al achilat matzah*
and you think about על אכילת מצה matzah *al achilat matzah* on
the פרוסה *prusa*. וכן עמא דבר וכן עושים על שלישית כריכה כדי
לקיים מצוה mitzvah. בשלשתן *v'chein ama davar v'chein osim al shlishis kericha
k'dei l'kayem mitzvah b'shloshtan* and we use the third one then for
כורך *korech* in order that you do all three. So this is
where we get our practice: two whole loaves because you're supposed to
always do two whole loaves, presumably on יום טוב *yom tov* and
presumably even on יום טוב *yom tov* of פסח Pesach *pesach*, although
the רי"ף *Rif* says that then one of them can be a
half. You need two whole, you need the half because that's the
half of לחם שעוני מברכין עליו דברים הרבה *lechem she'oni m'varchin alav
devarim harbeh*, it's the half that's in the מצה Matzah? *matzah* of
the סדר Seder *seder*, the מצה matzah *matzah* of מגיד Maggid *maggid*.
When you say the המוציא *hamotzi*, so the המוציא *hamotzi*, which is
the normal just ברכת המוציא *birchas hamotzi* of a יום טוב *yom
tov* meal, that should be on the שלמות *shleimos*, on the whole
one, it's also the bottom one, but the one you're going to
eat for המוציא *hamotzi*, presumably of course you need המוציא *hamotzi* for
any bread you're going to eat, but somehow we say the כוונה
*kavana* should be on the top שלם *shalem*, and then you drop
the bottom and then you could more emphasize the ברכה bracha. *bracha*
of על אכילת מצה matzah *al achilat matzah* is on the פרוסה
*prusa* which has been the symbolic מצה matzah *matzah* throughout the סדר
Seder *seder*. And then what we do is we take a כזית
kezayit *kezayit* of each. Now technically you don't really need a כזית
*kezayit* of each, because the כזית *kezayit* is only for the מצוה
mitzvah *mitzvah* of אכילת מצה matzah *achilat matzah*. You really would only
need a כזית *kezayit* of the broken one. המוציא *hamotzi* you could
have a crumb, even if you say there's an idea of your
עיקר כוונה *ikkar kavana* for המוציא *hamotzi* was the top, so have
a little bit. But somehow the practice developed that we say you're
supposed to have a כזית *kezayit* of each, of the top and
of the middle. There's never enough to go around anyway, so each
one gets a little of the top, a little of the middle
and then they משלימים *mashlim* it anyway. But then since we use
the bottom one for the לחם משנה mishna *lechem mishneh*, we're going
to wind up now making use of it for the כורך *korech*.
And because we broke the middle one, we use the other half
of what we broke for the אפיקומן *afikomen* and that's how all
the different components sort of come together. But again, a lot of
this isn't in the גמרא Gemara *gemara*, you can see how other
possibilities could have been possible.
I believe the רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* says one and a half.
Yes, I believe so, following the רי"ף *Rif*, that is correct,
one and a half.
That is correct.
So the practice is just to use the middle, just use the
broken one.
You have that in the beginning of תוספות, Tosafot he sounds like
that, but then he moves to, to this idea at the end.
So if the רא"ש Rosh and the רמב"ם Rambam hold the same
way, why doesn't the שלחן ערוך?
Shulchan Aruch? I don't, I have to check how the שלחן ערוך
Shulchan Aruch פוסק. paskens. I'm sorry, the רמ"א, Rama, the אשכנזים Ashkenazim
do like
תוספות Tosafos said. Okay, אף על פי שאין חרוסת מצוה, af al
pi she-ein charoset mitzvah, ואידך מצוה, ve-ilu mitzvah, so the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says it's not a
מצוה. mitzvah. If
it's not a מצוה mitzvah? משום מאי מייתי לה? mishum mai meitili?
Why are we bothering with it? אמר אמי משום קפא, Amar Ami
mishum kapa, like we said before, this type of a sap or
a bug in the מרור maror that can be dangerous and this
counteracts it. אמר אביי, Amar Abbaye, so then really there's no symbolism
according to this idea, there's no particular point of having it for
a סדר seder. purpose, just to deal with the מרור. maror. אמר
אביי קפא דחסא חמא, Amar Abbaye kapa de-chassa chama,
the way to deal with the either whatever, the bug or I'll
more interpret it as the sap, the pungency of the מרור maror
is a radish. That'll help, that'll help counteract that. קפא דחמא כרתי.
Kapa de-chama karsei. Now the way to deal with the pungency of
the radish is a cress. קפא דכרתי תמימי, Kapa de-karsei tamimi,
the way to deal with the pungency of the cress is to
have hot water. קפא דכולהו תמימי Kapa de-kulu tamimi actually, the way
to deal, counteract all of them is hot water. תיכא זו, Tika
zu, אדהכי והכי נימא הכי. ad hachi ve-hachi neima hachi. While you're
waiting for these other things to have their effect, counteract it, here's
what you should say, you see, you thought we were done with
incantations. קפא קפא דכירנא לך
יו, Kapa kapa de-chirnalach yu, poison or whatever, I recognize you, ולשבע
ובנתייך ule-shev u-venasayach and your seven daughters, ולתמני כלתייך ule-tamne kalatach and
your eight daughters-in-law. I have no idea. Moving along. רבי אליעזר או
רבי צדוק אומר מצוה. Rabbi Eliezer o Rabbi Tzadok omer mitzvah. רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer or רבי צדוק Rabbi Tzadok says that the חרוסת
charoset is a
מצוה. mitzvah מאי
מצוה? Mai mitzvah? What's the מצוה? mitzvah, רבי לוי אומר זכר לתפוח.
Rabbi Levi omer zecher le-tapuach. To remember the תפוח. tapuach. So the,
now because of the famous מדרש, midrash, which is in the גמרא
Gemara. in סוטה, Sotah, that the wives seduced their husbands, because they
didn't want to have sex because of what פרעה Paroh said, and
they said, you know, what, that's gonna be worse than what פרעה
Paroh said, because then there's no hope. So they seduced their husbands,
it says תחת התפוח tachas ha-tapuach by שיר השירים Shir HaShirim עוררתיך,
orarticha, I stirred you, and then because of that they had children,
and that ultimately led to the גאולה. geula. It,
by the way, the meaning of the word תפוח, tapuach, which we
translate as apple, is almost definitely incorrect, there were no apples in
the Near East and in the Middle East, it's a
apple actually is a sort of a generic for fruit, like you
know, what, like a potato is a pomme de terre, תפוח אדמה,
tapuach adama, תפוח tapuach just really means fruit. So the first thing
that אדם Adam and חוה Chava ate was almost definitely not an
apple. So there's a real question what תפוח tapuach means in שיר
השירים, Shir HaShirim, it's probably more of a citrus fruit. But anyway,
we do apples. What? Could be an אתרוג. esrog. Yeah, it's true.
Some say תפוח tapuach could be an אתרוג. esrog. Anyway, we do,
I had a friend who once told me that the famous מדרש
midrash says, you know, by עשו, Esav, it says, you know, it
says ריח בני כריח שדה אשר ברכו ה'. rei'ach beni ke-rei'ach sadeh
asher beiracho Hashem. He says, you know, what is that? פרדס של
תפוחים pardes shel tapuchim or something, he says, ever go into an
apple orchard? It smells awful. So it's clearly not apples. Anyway. All
right. Move on. So whatever תפוח tapuach is, it's a זכר לתפוח.
zecher le-tapuach. Okay, so something sharp and to remember this מדרש. midrash.
It's very funny of all the things we're right remembering, we're remembering
a מדרש midrash and not something, you know, that's like explicit, it
shows the power of the מדרש midrash on how much that becomes
part of the story. For רבי יוחנן אומר זכר לטיט. Rabbi Yochanan
omer zecher le-tit. No, it's thick, it's heavy, it reminds you of
the mortar.
אמר אביי הלכך, Amar Abaye hilkach, because of those two concerns, those
two ideas, צריך לכהויי, tzarich le-kahavuye, you have to make it pungent,
sharp, וצריך לסמוכיה, ve-tzarich le-samchu-e,
you have to make it thick. לכהויי זכר לתפוח, le-kahavuye zecher le-tapuach,
sharp to remember the תפוח, tapuach, וצריך לסמוכיה זכר לטיט, ve-tzarich le-samchu-e
zecher le-tit, and thick because of the mortar. תני כוותיה דרבי יוחנן,
Tanna ke-vatch de-Rabbi Yochanan, we talk about רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, תבלין
זכר לתבן. tavlin zecher le-teven. So the תבלין, tavlin, the spices to
remember the תבן, teven, it could be just the play on words,
תבלין tavlin and תבן, teven, it could also be that if the
spices are not like we have these nice McCormick round spices, but
if you basically think of like of a cinnamon stick and you
put the cinnamon in and you crush them, so it's זכר לתבן,
zecher le-teven, the רמב"ם Rambam actually says that you put certain pieces
of like, you know, straw or whatever into it and you don't
even crush it, you just leave it whole. זכר לתבן, zecher le-teven,
I think so, I have to check what his recipe again. Anyway,
so תבלין זכר לתבן, tavlin zecher le-teven, חרוסת, charoset, the whole חרוסת
charoset combined is זכר לטיט, zecher le-tit, to remember the mortar. אמר
רבי אליעזר בר צדוק כך היו אומרים תגרי חרך שבירושלים,
Amar Rabbi Eliezer bar Tzadok kach
hayu omrim tagre cherach she-bi-Yerushalayim, those that sell חרך, cherach, exactly what.
exactly what חרך cherach is. רש״י Rashi says it means those that
sell in the little niches in the wall in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. This
is what they used to say: בואו וטלו לכם תבלין למצוה. bo
u'telu lachem tavlin l'mitzvah. Get your spices for the מצוה Mitzvah of
חרוסת. charoset. And the general assumption is that we rule like רבי
אלעזר ברבי צדוק Rabbi Elazar bar Rabbi Tzadok and we say that
obviously it has this symbolism and because of that we're מקפיד makpid
about certain ingredients exactly to have this type of symbolism. רמב״ם Rambam
in פירוש המשניות Perush Hamishnayot says according to רבי אלעזר ברבי צדוק
Rabbi Elazar bar Rabbi Tzadok that it's a מצוה, mitzvah you would
actually say a ברכה bracha on it, על אכילת חרוסת. al achilat
charoset. Nobody says that, but again showing the רמב״ם Rambam I don't
and I don't think the רמב״ם Rambam says you have to eat
a כזית of this. But anyway, if you want to take a
look at some of the ingredients, some of the recipes,
צריך לסומכי tzarich l'somchei תוספות tosafos says,
וצריך לחפויי, u'tzarich l'chapuyei, ירושלמי Yerushalmi אמר איסט אבדי זכר לדם. amar
ist avdi zecher l'dam. How about the blood? ומשום הכי קרי ליה
טיבולא במשקה. u'mishum hachi karei lei tibula b'mashkeh. This was the question
I asked before. Why is חרוסת charoset called משקה? mashkeh? Where's the
משקה mashkeh in it? So תוספות Tosafos says no, because you would
add wine to it and that makes it a משקה. mashkeh. ומשום
umishum וכן אמר דבר v'chen amar davar this is the tradition ולסומכי
ולסומכי u'lsamchei u'lsamchei to make it thick ובשעת אכילה מקלישין אותו ביין
u'vishat achilah maklishin oto b'yayin וחומץ v'chometz then you sort of you
know you dilute it somewhat it's not just a thick mass with
wine and with vinegar and that actually is why it was called
a משקה mashkeh before. Okay, so there you get the wine. ובתשובות
הגאונים מפרש לעשות חרוסת בפירות שנדמתה כנסת ישראל בשיר השירים: u'btshuvot ha-Geonim
meforesh la'asot charoset b'perot shenidmeila knesset Yisrael b'Shir HaShirim: תחת התפוח עוררתיך,
tachat hatapuach orarticha, כפלח הרמון, k'felach harimon, התאנה חנטה פגיה, hate'enah chanta
fageha,
אמרתי אעלה בתמר, amarti eleh b'tamar, אגוז אל גינת אגוז egoz el
ginat egoz ושקדים שם ששקד הקדוש ברוך הוא על הקץ. u'shkedim she-Shem
sheshakad HaKadosh Baruch Hu al hakeitz. So there you get a lot
of nice things, the nuts and the and the wine and you
also get pomegranates and figs and dates and so on. Yes, Josh.
I've just heard what Charlie muttered under his breath.
What did he mutter?
A very deep resonance.
Jews in the middle ages at the time of תוספות accused of
blood libel during פסח Pesach. and we have a strong tradition for
symbolic food symbolizing blood. Right. These things always have some type of
echo, you know somebody heard something.
Could be, right.
It's really yeah tricky thinking about this historical thing. People don't make
stuff up like no.
Right, right, right, that's excellent. Okay, let's take a look now at
the next משנה. mishna So we did קדש ורחץ כרפס יחץ Kadesh
Urchatz Karpas Yachatz and we began sort of מגיד Maggid talking about
the קערה keara but we have not gotten to the other to
the real מגיד and that's this משנה. Mishnah מזגו לו כוס שני,
mazgu lo kos sheni, they the attendants poured a second cup of
wine, okay, after you did basically the כרפס karpas or the מרור
maror according to the משנה Mishnah and now we understand you do
a יחץ. וכאן הבן שואל v'kan haben shoel and here at this
point is where the child asks, אביו aviv his father, ואם אין
דעת בבן אביו מלמדו v'im ein daat baben aviv melamdo and if
the father doesn't know how to if the child doesn't know how
to ask the father instructs him. מה נשתנה הלילה הזה מכל הלילות?
Mah nishtanah halailah hazeh mikol haleilot? I have a lot to say
about this but first let's read it and translate it. How is
this night different than all other nights? שבכל הלילות אנו אוכלין חמץ
ומצה הלילה הזה כולו מצה. she-bechol haleilot anu ochlin chametz u'matzah halailah
hazeh kulo matzah. Other nights it's חמץ and מצה this night just
מצה. שבכל הלילות אנו אוכלין שאר ירקות הלילה הזה מרור. she-bechol haleilot
anu ochlin shear yerakot halailah hazeh maror. Other nights other vegetables, this
night only מרור maror or מרור. moror. שבכל הלילות אנו אוכלין בשר
צלי שלוק ומבושל, she-bechol haleilot anu ochlin basar tzali shaluk u'mevushal, normally
eat roasted, boiled, and cooked, הלילה הזה כולו צלי, halailah hazeh kulo
tzali, this night it's only it's only roasted. שבכל הלילות אנו she-bechol
haleilot anu there's a couple versions of the גרסא, girsa, אין אנו
חייבין לטבול ein anu chayavin litbol or אנו מטבילין פעם אחת הלילה
הזה שתי פעמים. anu matbilin paam echat halailah hazeh shtei feamim. We'll
see about that in the גמרא. Gemara לפי דעתו של בן אביו
מלמדו, lefi daato shel ben aviv melamdo, based on the understanding of
the child the father teaches him. מתחיל בגנות, matchil b'gnut, you start
with the more derogatory
denigration ומסיים בשבח u'msayeim b'shevach and you end with the laudatory. ודורש
מארמי אובד אבי עד שיגמור כל הפרשה כולה. v'doresh me-Arami oved avi
ad she-yigmor kol haparsha kulo. You expound on ארמי אובד אבי, Arami
oved avi, the פרשה parsha of ביכורים bikkurim until you finish expounding
the whole פרשה. parsha. So here is a totally much more freestyle.
Here is the basic thing. It starts with the מה נשתנה Mah
nishtanah questions and it talks about a general structure from עבדות לחרות
avdut l'cheirut and it gives you the basic format that you use
expounding on ארמי אובד אבי. Arami oved avi. So those are the
three major components. We're going to see in the next משנה Mishnah.
רבן גמליאל היה אומר שלשה דברים אלו בפסח, Rabban Gamliel hayah omer
sheloshah devarim elu b'Pesach, tying in the symbolism, but the basic questions
structure is and this is important to note: questions, responding to questions,
דרשנינג darshening the פסוקים psukim and the basic trajectory of עבדות לחרות.
avdut l'cheirut. So let's talk about each one of these. So in
terms of first of all the questions. First it's worth noting that
we have four questions. That's for us it's very important to have
four, so when we take out the idea of roasted we replace
it with the idea of reclining. Nevertheless, a number of משניות mishnayot
only have three. The גמרא Gemara, never calls it four questions. הרי״ף
haRif only has three. I'm trying to remember which three הרי״ף haRif
has. הרי״ף haRif says אנו מטבילין
פעם אחת, anu matbilin paam echat, חמץ ומצה chametz u'matzah and צלי.
tzali. He doesn't have the מרור maror one. Okay, so that's interesting
number one to note that some גרסאות girsas don't have
don't have four. Number two, what is this issue here about the
צלי? tseli? So if you take a look at the רשבם, Rashbam,
I mean obviously we don't say it, we don't have a פסח.
Pesach. You take a look at the רשבם, Rashbam, he says בזמן
שבית המקדש קיים היה שונה. bizman she'Beis Ha'Mikdash kayam haya shoneh. Okay,
this was the time of the Beis HaMikdash. However, you might remember
that the earlier Mishnah said ובזמן המקדש u'vizman Ha'Mikdash
what does it say היו מביאים לפניו גופו של פסח, hayu mevi'im
lefanav gufo shel Pesach, right? Remember that? It says ובמקדש היו מביאים
לפניו גופו של פסח. u'be'Mikdash hayu mevi'im lefanav gufo shel Pesach. The
משנה mishnah, in קט"ד Kuf Tes Daled when it talks about bringing
the מצה, which means now that our frame of reference is not
מקדש. Mikdash. And nevertheless it says כולו צלי. kulo tseli. And there
is a very good reason to think that this is talking about
not זמן המקדש zman Ha'Mikdash and it is following the מנהג minhag
that we learned about way back in the fourth פרק perek that
you would eat דווקא, davka, one way of understanding it is דווקא
davka eat צלי tseli בליל פסח be'leil Pesach זכר לפסח. zecher le'Pesach.
We now have so bracketed that because we are influenced by the
later development from the בבלי Bavli that says you can't even, maybe
you shouldn't even have roast meat is our מנהג, minhag, you know,
on ליל סדר, Seder? you don't point to the meat when you
say בשר זה, basar zeh, etc. because חס ושלום chas v'shalom it
should look like you're like you're you know מקדיש קדשים בחוץ. makdish
kodshim bachutz. But nevertheless there was an opposite מנהג minhag really earlier
after the חורבן churban because they wanted to hold on to the
קרבן פסח korban Pesach that they would דווקא davka have צלי tseli
and they would even roast a kid goat and we heard that
people would call it a פסח. Pesach? Obviously it got a little
overboard, but you could understand that actually maybe דווקא davka they did
have צלי tseli and they did say כולו צלי kulo tseli even
בזמן bizman even אחר זמן המקדש. achar zman Ha'Mikdash. That's about the
צלי tseli issue. Now,
what is here the side, by the way, now obviously or maybe
it's not obvious I should say it, the reason, you know, people
ask a question, how is the מצווה mitzvah סיפור יציאת מצרים sippur
yetzias Mitzrayim on ליל סדר Seder. different than the מצווה mitzvah the
rest of the year when you're supposed to every day remember זכר
ליציאת מצרים? zecher li'yetzias Mitzrayim? And there are a number of ways
in which it's different. It's different that it has the symbols. It's
different that you tell it at length and you tell the whole
story, you don't just mention but you narrate, you relate, you describe
as we see although this is less clear in the פסוקים, pesukim,
it comes through expounding on verses. Okay, but one way it's key
different is the time, the whole idea of כי ישאלך בנך מחר
לאמר ki yishalcha bincha machar l'emor that there's a sense of questions
and responding and stimulating the questions and the type of engagement you
have when people are curious and asking questions and giving answers is
obviously a very different experience. So all that discussion of כדי שישאלו
התינוקות kedei she'yishalu ha'tinokos and this issue of כאן הבן שואל kan
haben sho'el is because of the structure that is in the פסוקים
pesukim of כי ישאלך בנך מחר לאמר ki yishalcha bincha machar l'emor
and we want to get that structure of questioning and responding and
stimulating it and we've provided a text and that is what part
of what makes the מצווה mitzvah of הגדה haggadah distinct and unique.
Now, how about the issue of the what do you call it?
About how does the child ask questions before he has seen them?
Okay, so that's you know he hasn't yet seen the צלי. tseli.
He, the מרור maror we discussed according to the משנה mishnah. actually
you did the first dipping in the מרור, maror, okay. The מצה
presumably he's noticed that there's no nothing else in the house. But
some of this right, the you know the צלי tseli yet has
not yet occurred and the what do you call it, the
what's the other one that I skipped? There's the מרור, maror, the
צלי, tseli, the dipping, oh the dipping, the dipping occurred once so
that you could ask because if they didn't normally dip before the
meal. But some of this stuff right, they don't know yet the
שתי פעמים. shtei pe'amim. So that's why תוספות says as I said
that when you remove the table and he asks what's that about?
You feed him the lines. Oh don't worry we're going to have
מרור, maror, we're going to have dipping, we're going to do this,
and that gets him to ask these questions. But that obviously is
a problem here. And interesting that a number
of commentators more recent commentators have suggested but it really is in
the רמב"ם Rambam says that the word the that the מה נשתנה
הלילה הזה Mah Nishtanah Ha'lailah Ha'zeh is not the question, it's the
answer. It's not למה נשתנה. lama nishtanah. It's the child asks whatever
the child asks you get him to ask and then you say
אב ושלמדו av u'she'limdo you teach him let me point out to
you מה נשתנה הלילה הזה מכל הלילות Mah Nishtanah Ha'lailah Ha'zeh mikol
ha'leilos how different tonight is, I want to make it clear to
you and I'm going to show you how different tonight is than
all other nights. And then you might get him to say well
why is that? Right you present him with that reality and then
maybe he asks well why are we having those differences? The רמב"ם
Rambam actually says that, the רמב"ם Rambam's says the child asks and
the person who says the הגדה haggadah says מה נשתנה הלילה הזה
מכל הלילות Mah Nishtanah Ha'lailah Ha'zeh mikol ha'leilos the דוגמה dugma of
מה טובו, Mah Tovu, exactly.
Okay, so that really says. Now if one last point and then
we'll move on to the גמרא, Gemara. if it actually is the
child asking the question is what's the answer? When do you give
the answer? Now the interesting thing is you know what? There is
an answer, it's just a big interruption cause if you look at
the very bottom of the page רבן גמליאל היה אומר כל שלא
אמר שלשה דברים אלו בפסח לא יצא ידי חובתו פסח מצה ומרור.
Rabban Gamliel haya omer kol shelo amar shlosha devarim eilu ba'Pesach lo
yatza yedei chovaso, Pesach, Matzah, u'Maror. What do we... Why do we
eat the פסח? pasach Why do we eat the מצה? Why do
we eat the מרור? Maror? Guess what, those were three of the
four questions that were asked in the מה נשתנה, Mah Nishtanah, because
it asked about the צלי tzli as well in the original version,
right? So that was three of the four questions are answered by
the time you get to רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. It is just
that we, you know, have a big interruption until we actually get
there. It almost makes it- oh, I see what you are saying
is, oh, you know what? Let me tell you a story and
we will find out what the answer is. It is a good
point, but you have got to frame it to know that this
is going to lead in. After we tell the whole story, you
will appreciate why we are doing these things. But I do not
think that we appreciate how the רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel is really,
I think, ultimately answering it. And right, and this is the story
that explains it. Okay, let us take a look now at the
גמרא. Gemara: תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. חכם בנו שואלו. Chacham beno shoalo.
If
you are- if-
so חכם בנו Chacham beno is probably the right way to read
it. It means if the son knows how to ask, then the
son is the one who asks. It is not about you being
a חכם, chacham, it is about your son being a חכם. chacham.
חכם בנו. Chacham beno.
Right, חכם בנו, Chacham beno, that is what I just said. חכם
בנו, Chacham beno, right, right, but then ושואלו, veshoalo, right, but it
misses the subject of who is the שואלו. shoalo. But right,
חכם בנו שואלו. Chacham beno shoalo. ואם אינו חכם, Ve'im eino chacham,
if the son is not a חכם, chacham, אשתו שואלתו. ishto shoalto.
Then you need- again, it is assuming obviously that the man in
the house is leading the הגדה Haggadah and is the one that
is expounding, although we spoke about everybody having a Seder plate before
then. So you get- then the Torah speaks about the child asking,
if there is no child then the wife asks. ואם לאו, Ve'im
lav,
and if there is no one else around the house or nobody
who could ask him, הוא שואל את עצמו. hu shoal et atzmo.
He asks himself. It is not crazy when you ask yourself questions,
it is a good way of pushing yourself to explore things.
ואפילו שני תלמידי חכמים שיודעים בהלכות הפסח שואלים זה לזה, Ve'afilu shnei
talmidei chachamim sheyodi'in behilchot hapesach shoalin zeh lazeh, and even two תלמידי
חכמים talmidei chachamim ask one another because of the structure of question
and answer, even if it cannot be fulfilled with a child, is
an important structure of telling the story. Yes.
And the שואלו shoalo then is whatever it is that they ask,
you know. Well, that depends.
If the מה נשתנה
Mah
Nishtanah is the text of the question, then it means the question.
If the מה נשתנה Mah Nishtanah is an answer, then they ask
whatever questions are on their mind and they should be asking in
this response. Now, you know, and that is again we incorporate some
of that in our things, you know, that אפילו חכמים מצוה עלינו
לספר, afilu chachamim mitzvah aleinu lesaper, etc. Here it is not just
about the סיפור, sippur, here it is about the questioning. It is
interesting that it says שיודעים בהלכות הפסח. sheyodi'in behilchot hapesach. You might
know a lot of הלכה, halachah, you might not have thought enough
about the story, right? So that is also, you know, interesting about
maybe that is part of the point and that you have to
start asking about the story. שואלים- Shoalin there is an interesting question
of how much does the מצות סיפור יציאת מצרים mitzvat sippur yetziat
mitzrayim include talking about the הלכות halachot of ליל סדר. Seder מה
נשתנה הלילה הזה מכל הלילות שבכל הלילות אנו מטבילין פעם אחת הלילה
הזה שתי פעמים. Mah nishtanah halaylah hazeh mikol halaylot shebechol halaylot anu
matbilin pa'am achat halaylah hazeh shtei pe'amim. So that was the גירסא
girsa of the גמרא: Gemara all of the nights we dip once,
tonight twice. מתקיף לה רבא. Matkif lah Rava. So רבא Rava said,
אטו כל יומא לא סגי דלא מטבעי חדא זמנא? atu kol yoma
lo sagi delo matbe'ei chada zimna? What do you mean all of
the nights we dip once? Why, you have to dip once every
single night? אלא אמר רבא, Ela amar Rava, so rather says רבא,
Rava, הכי קתני: hachi ktani: שבכל הלילות אין אנו חייבים לטבול אפילו
פעם אחת, shebechol haleilot ein anu chayavin litbol afilu pa'am achat, all
of the nights we do not have to and are not obligated,
הלילה הזה שתי פעמים, halaylah hazeh shtei pe'amim, now we have to
do it twice. מתקיף לה רב ספרא. Matkif lah Rav Safra. רב
ספרא Rav Safra said, חיובי לדרדקי? chiyuva ledardakei? What, it is an
obligation for the kids? Meaning although we dip twice so the kids
should ask, it is not like a חיוב, chiyuv, it is not
like a sense of a real obligation, it is just a practice.
אלא אמר רב ספרא הכי קתני: Ela amar Rav Safra hachi ktani:
אין אנו מטבילין אפילו פעם אחת, ein anu matbilin afilu pa'am achat,
not that we do once, but we do not do it once,
meaning we do not implicitly like we do not have to but
we do not go out of our way to do it even
once, הלילה הזה שתי פעמים, halaylah hazeh shtei pe'amim, now we go
out of our way to do it twice. So it is sort
of like have to, but without saying חיוב. chiyuv. We go out
of our way. The same way when we say by the vegetables,
you know, אנו אוכלין שאר ירקות. anu ochlin she'ar yerakot. What, you
have to eat vegetables other nights? I guess if you listen to
your mother you do, but anyway, but it means that we, you
know, we do not make a point of eating מרור. maror. So
here too we make a point of doing it twice. Okay, מתחיל
בגנות, matchil bignut, so that is the questions and we discussed that
whole structure of responding to questions and now comes the structure of
the answer.
מתחיל בגנות ומסיים בשבח. matchil bignut umesayem beshevach. מאי בגנות? Mai bignut?
What is the sort of, you know,
denigration? רב אמר מתחלה עובדי עבודה זרה היו אבותינו. Rav amar matchila
ovdei avodah zarah hayu avoteinu. Our forefathers used to be idolaters. ושמואל
אמר עבדים היינו. Ushmuel amar avadim hayinu. No, we used to be
slaves. So now this is of course two ways of telling the
story. Is it a story about physical freedom and independence and autonomy
and so on? Is it a story about being redeemed to be
בני בכורי ישראל Beni Bechori Yisrael and עבדי הם אשר הוצאתי אותם
מארץ מצרים? avadai hem asher hotzeti otam me'eretz mitzrayim? It is being
redeemed to be God's people and ultimately a story that culminates at
מעמד הר סיני. Ma'amad Har Sinai. So if you look at the
הגדה Haggadah we do both רב Rav, and שמואל, Shmuel, right? If
we take a look, right, after the מה נשתנה, Mah Nishtanah, מחזיר
את הקערה, machzir et hake'arah, and you know, עבדים היינו לפרעה במצרים.
avadim hayinu lePharaoh beMitzrayim. Right, so you give the short answer, which
is the simple answer, the simple story of it according to שמואל.
Shmuel. Well then you do the כנגד ארבעה בנים. Ke'neged Arba'ah Banim.
Again, it’s interesting why we double back. I can’t really explain that.
After we do the asking, we double back to talk about this
framework of the asking, but maybe it also means, you know, it’s
sort of like a חכם בנו-ish Chacham Beno issue, that there are
different types of people at the table. And before you get into
a longer telling over of the story, you have to tailor your
story to the different people that are at the table, the children
or whoever's at the table. So we bring in the כנגד ארבעה
בנים. Ke'neged Arba'ah Banim. And then when we start, before we get
to
דורש מארמי אובד אבי, Doresh Me'Arami Oved Avi, מתחילה עובדי עבודה זרה
היו אבותינו ועכשיו קרבנו המקום לעבודתו. Mitchilah Ovdei Avodah Zarah Hayu Avoteinu
Ve'achshav Kervanu HaMakom La'avodato. So we have the first short answer according
to שמואל, Shmuel, short answer according to רב, Rav and then we
expound. I can’t tell you why the כנגד ארבעה בנים Ke'neged Arba'ah
Banim appears before, between the רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, but it’s
clear that it should appear before you start to elaborate. And that
is obviously two different ways to tell about what the story, about
what has been happening. One minute left, let's finish to the משנה.
mishnah, אמר ליה רב נחמן לדרו עבדיה, Amar Leih Rav Nachman Le'Darru
Avdeih, רב נחמן Rav Nachman said to דרו Darru his servant, his
slave, excuse me, עבדא דמפיק ליה מריה לחירות, Avda De'mappik Leih Mareih
Le'cheirus, if a slave were to be freed by his master to
freedom, ויהיב ליה כספא ודהבא, Ve'yahiv Leih Kaspa Ve'dahava, and were to
give him gold and silver, מאי בעי למימר ליה, Mai Ba'ei Le'meimar
Leih, what should the slave say? It’s not a real fair question
to ask a slave.
You’re sort of a little bit of a tease or a lot
of a tease. אמר ליה, Amar Leih, he said to him, בעי
לאודויי ולשבוחי, Ba'ei Le'oduyei U'leshabbuchi, oh, he would thank him, he would
praise him! אמר ליה, Amar Leih, he said, great, פטרתן מלומר מה
נשתנה. Patartan Mi'lomar Ma Nishtana. We don’t have to say מה נשתנה.
Ma Nishtana. Okay, goodbye, go back to being a slave.
פתח ואמר עבדים היינו. Patach Ve'amar Avadim Hayinu. He opened and said
עבדים היינו. Avadim Hayinu. Now by the way, that very much tells
you right after מה נשתנה, Ma Nishtana, what’s the first thing you
say? עבדים היינו. Avadim Hayinu. So there you have that idea of
that structure according to שמואל, Shmuel, עבדים היינו. Avadim Hayinu. But the
other interesting thing is what do you mean פטרתן מלומר מה נשתנה?
Patartan Mi'lomar Ma Nishtana? He didn’t give a question, he gave an
answer. So this might suggest that the מה נשתנה Ma Nishtana is
a beginning of an answer, it’s not a question. But it’s a
little strange
because he’s about to give an answer, עבדים היינו Avadim Hayinu and
so on. So how exactly this got them out of מה נשתנה
Ma Nishtana is not so clear. Before, when רבא Rava said why
are we removing the table or was it אביי Abaye said why
are we removing the table, you got us out of מה נשתנה,
Ma Nishtana, that was clearly a question, a curiosity, we’re going to
respond to it. How exactly here this is seen as a parallel
to מה נשתנה Ma Nishtana is less clear. Yeah, there was a
question? Yes.
Do you know when we mention idol worship and then slavery both,
and this question of when השם Hashem tells אברהם Avraham they’re going
to be in Egypt for the slavery, it seems like the תיקון
Tikkun for having had idol worship?
I mean, that’s possible, although the sense of the guilt of idol
worship, although that we have the תיקון Tikkun in a metaphysical sense,
I mean not in a sin sense, it was before, it wasn’t
sort of look, that’s a much larger discussion. That’s a discussion we
can have at סדר night about what was the purpose of the
שעבוד. Shibbud.
But I suppose you could say that. I that’s not the way
I tend to think about it, but you know, it’s a possibility.
I want to say something about before we run into שלשה דברים
Shlosha Devarim because what the גמרא Gemara. completely skips over is the
דורש מארמי אובד אבי, Doresh Me'Arami Oved Avi, right? And why using
that as a structure? And I’ll just say one sense of it.
It’s very strange because you would think that what you’re supposed to
be doing, the best way to tell the story is open up
שמות, Shemot, read the story, tell the story. But ארמי אובד אבי
Arami Oved Avi is significant. ארמי אובד אבי Arami Oved Avi is
the one place in the תורה where you have a retelling of
the story in a ritual context, right? The person brings the ביכורים
Bikkurim and he does a retelling of ארמי אובד אבי. Arami Oved
Avi. And part of the whole point of the הגדה Haggadah is
not just telling over somebody else's story, not just reading a book
as it were, or audiobooks, right? We’re going to have audiobooks on
שמות. Shemot. It’s a retelling. And when you retell a story, then
you bring into it your framing, what you want to emphasize, you
know, particular dimensions you want to look at. The retelling has a
very personal power that the telling does not. And that's part of
the idea of דורש. Doresh. The whole idea of דורש, Doresh, of
תורה שבעל פה Torah She'be'al Peh is the sort of intersection of
the human with the divine,
normally you talk about in terms of הלכה Halacha and interpretation, but
it's the same thing in terms of the telling of the story.
So we have already this idea of retelling and we use that
as the framework for us to do a retelling of a retelling,
for us to do our דרשה, Derashah, and for us to give
insight
in those פסוקים. Pesukim. Of course now everybody just reads a fixed
text of the הגדה, Haggadah, but that wasn’t the basic structure and
it's quite significant that the דורש Doresh becomes a central part of
it. It's also just worth thinking to the way in which this
is also influenced in general by a concept of תלמוד תורה, Talmud
Torah, not just of telling a story. What do I mean by
that? Number one, I alluded to before in the תוספתא Tosefta that
speaks about, you know, that the מצוה mitzvah is not only to
tell the story but to talk about הלכות הפסח. Hilchos HaPasach. Think
about what we say to the חכם, Chacham, אף אתה אמור לו
כהלכות הפסח. Af Atah Emor Lo Ke'hilchos HaPasach. Since when are we
talking about הלכות הפסח? Hilchos HaPasach? Number one, שנאמר תלמידי חכמים היודעים
בהלכות הפסח. She'ne'emar Talmidei Chachamim Ha'yode'im Be'hilchos HaPasach. And the whole point,
ברוך המקום ברוך הוא, Baruch HaMakom Baruch Hu, ברוך שנתן תורה לעמו
ישראל Baruch Shenasan Torah l'amo Yisrael is a mini ברכת התורה. Birchas
HaTorah. So the way in which thinking of the סיפור יציאת מצרים
sippur yetzias mitzrayim is a type of a תלמוד תורה talmud torah
is another theme that sort of gets introduced here, and דורש doresh
מארמי אובד אבי me-arami oved avi is classic תלמוד תורה. talmud torah.
It's חז"ל's, chazal the rabbinic enterprise of תורה שבעל פה. torah she-ba'al
peh. Yes, Rivka?
Are
we lost into ארמי אובד אבי arami oved avi and מצרים mitzrayim
together, because מצרים mitzrayim to Abraham?
Hey, you know what? דורש, doresh, go for it! I'm serious, I'm
serious. You know, well, in the משנה, mishnah. it does seem that
they had some text as we're going to see in the next
משנה. Mishna, By the way, the fact that he says פתח ואמר
עבדים היינו, pasach v'amar avadim hayinu, right, sounds like there was a
fixed text. You know, even when רב and שמואל Shmuel say עבדים
היינו, avadim hayinu, מתחילה עובדי עבודה זרה, matchilah ovdei avodah zarah, maybe
they were just pointing to different parts of a text that they
all agreed on. Maybe their text had both components.
But ארמי אובד אבי arami oved avi is...
Right, so my point is that in the משנה, Mishna it does
not seem like there's a fixed text to how you're דורש doresh
ארמי אובד אבי, arami oved avi, but you don't know, but you
don't know. I mean, again, I would not want to be advocating
drop the fixed text of the thing, but if you wanted to
read it and then you wanted to focus on, here's what I
really think it's talking about, I think that's a big קיום kiyum
in the הגדה. haggadah. It's supposed to be your take on those
things.
And today, we believe in that.
They were totally, they were definitely leaving a lot open. Yes, Charlie.
Some of us had more recent ancestors who were worshipping idols.
Oh, there you go. Okay, let's take a look at, yes.
Interesting point and דורש doresh is
דורש את עצמו doresh es atzmo in order to understand how a
slave was really, how a person...
To try to, to try to, for himself, you know, get that,
right, you know, right, empathizing and getting that feeling, could be, that
could be that that's why he was introduced, he was asking דורש.
doresh. Okay, so now let's take a look at... it's actually an
interesting question, right, because an עבד כנעני eved kena'ani חייב במצוות, chayav
b'mitzvos, so you know, does עבדים avadim have the מצוה mitzvah of
סיפור יציאת מצרים? sippur yetzias mitzrayim?
Yeah, I first thought of it, it's a really interesting question.
Someone actually had come up before that חירות cheirus here is associated
with wealth and power.
Well, yes, we have
discussed זהב וכסף. zahav v'chesef. But that was also part of the
story, right, they came out with gold and silver.
Right, of all the
things, all the things to mention, right, it's a good point, why
of all things emphasize that? Okay, let's look at the משנה. Mishna.
רבן גמליאל היה אומר: Rabban Gamliel hayah omer: כל שלא אמר
שלשה דברים אלו בפסח לא יצא ידי חובתו.
kol shelo amar
shlosha
devarim elu b'pesach lo yatza yeday chovaso. If you didn't say these
three things, you didn't fulfill your obligation. We already pointed out how
they to a large degree answered the question.
ואלו הן, v'elu hen, these are they: פסח מצה ומרור. pesach matzah
umaror. פסח על שום שפסח המקום על בתי אבותינו במצרים, pesach al
shum she-pasach HaMakom al batei avosaynu b'Mitzrayim, שנאמר, shenemar, ואמרתם זבח פסח
הוא לה' אשר פסח. v'amartem zevach pesach hu l'Adonai asher pasach.
Now,
by the way, that not only is telling you the symbolism, אשר
פסח על בתי אבותינו במצרים. asher pasach al batei avosaynu b'Mitzrayim. By
the way, פסח pesach could mean to skip over, hop over, could
also mean to save. Some say the word פסח pasach. means actually
to save, פסח. pesach So anyway, that's a question of what the
word פסח pesach itself means. But anyway, but תוספות points out that
part of the point according to this פסוק pasuk is ואמרתם זבח
פסח, v'amartem zevach pesach, that on the eating of the פסח Pesach,
you explain its significance. And that's what he's saying is you have
to say these things, you have to say and explain the significance
as we see the פסוק pasuk itself talks about explaining the significance.
מצה על שום שנגאלו אבותינו, matzah al shum she-nig'alu avosaynu, שנאמר ויאפו
את הבצק אשר הוציאו. shenemar vayofu es habatzek asher hotziu. Right, now
we're up to the point where מצה emphasizes freedom. מרור על שום
שמררו המצריים את חיי אבותינו במצרים. maror al shum she-mar'ru ha-mitzriyim es
chayay avosaynu b'Mitzrayim. Some have מרורין, marorin, not מרור, maror, because that's
the language of the פסוק, pasuk, שנאמר וימררו את חייהם. shenemar vay'mar'ru
es chayayhem. Okay, going back though. Right, I know, okay, pointed it
out. Anyway, so, now, before we go on, I want to, okay,
before we go to the next part, obviously here we are now
dealing with things that have become components of the סדר. When it
now, because רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel said, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel said this, excuse me, רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel said
this. But there's an interesting question. If you didn't say it, לא
יצא ידי חובתו, lo yatza yeday chovaso, which חיוב chiyuv have you
not been יוצא? yotzei? First of all, there's a question the ראשונים
ask if he literally means לא יצא ידי חובתו lo yatza yeday
chovaso or is he sort of, you know, or is he, you
know, or is he just exaggerating a little bit, is it rhetoric?
But even whether he means it literally or not, what חיוב chiyuv
have you not been יוצא yotzei or not been יוצא yotzei ideally?
To what you
most logically say, what חיוב chiyuv have you not been יוצא? yotzei?
חיוב הגדה, chiyuv haggadah, right. So we talked about the child asking,
we talked about responding,
we talked about דורש. doresh. Part of that has to be explaining
the symbolisms of everything that you're eating, and that certainly is the
generally accepted פשט pshat that it's worth noting that some ראשונים understand
that one of the חיובים chiyuvim you might not be יוצא yotzei
fully or wholly is the חיוב chiyuv of אכילת מצה, the חיוב
chiyuv of אכילת מרור, achilas maror, the חיוב chiyuv of אכילת פסח.
achilas pesach.
That maybe the מצוה mitzvah of סיפור sippur requires the integration of
the symbols and explicating it, not just eating them and having them,
it could be the מצוה mitzvah. of the אכילה achilah requires the
giving of its symbolism through the telling of the story. So that
is an interesting question about how these two work together. And what
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel was saying is, and we shouldn't pass over,
pass over it, is, is, it's not just having them there, it's
not just having them... eating them, it's not just בפני כל אחד
ואחד, b'fnei kol echad v'echad, it's actually pulling them into the story
and making them a part of the story itself. Okay, so that's
רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. So by the way, if you look at
your הגדה, Haggadah, right? So we have, I think צא ולמד tzei
u'l'mad is where you begin, right? We didn't do the והיא שעמדה,
v'hi she'amda, that's a new thing. Every time you lift up the
כוס, kos, you cover the מצה because of the whole idea of,
you know, the מצה has precedence over the כוס, kos, so you
have to cover it up. Anyway, but then you tell do the
whole צא, tzei, you put the כוס kos down, you uncover because
of עונים עליו דברים הרבה, onim alav devarim harbei, צא ולמד, tzei
u'l'mad, you do the whole, you know, the whole thing about דרוש
מארמי אובד אבי, Darosh me'Arami Oved Avi, then you have the whole
thing about, you know, whatever, the דיינו, Dayenu, etc. Anyway, you have
basically that whole trajectory, and then you're nearing the end, רבן גמליאל
אומר כל שלא אמר שלשה דברים אלו. Rabban Gamliel omer kol shelo
amar shlosha devarim eilu. You tie it into the symbols. פסח שהיו,
Pesach shehayu, מצה זו, Matzah zu, מרור זה, Maror zeh, etc. And
then what's the next thing? אוחז הכוס בידו ויאחז המצה ויאמר, Yochaz
hakhos biyado ve'yachaz hamatzah ve'yomar, לפיכך אנחנו חייבים להודות. lefikhakh anachnu chayavim
lehodot. You've told the whole story, you've tied it into the symbolisms,
and therefore you now becomes the הלל, Hallel, introducing what we've reached
גאולה, Geula, we have to give להודות lehodot and give שבח shevach
etc. and that is now the גמרא. Gemara Oh, I jumped ahead.
בכל דור ודור חייב אדם לראות את עצמו כאילו הוא יצא ממצרים,
bekhol dor vador chayav adam lirot et atzmo k'ilu hu yatza miMitzrayim,
שנאמר והגדת לבנך ביום ההוא לאמר בעבור זה עשה ה' לי בצאתי
ממצרים. shene'emar ve'higadeta l'vincha bayom hahu leimor ba'avur zeh asa Hashem li
betzeiti miMitzrayim. Is רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel saying all this still? It's
not now it sounds like, I was going to point it out,
it sounds like now we are not just in a משנה, Mishna.
we are actually quoting a text of הגדה. Haggadah. Okay, as you'll
see, like לפיכך אנחנו חייבים להודות להלל לשבח לפאר לרומם להדר לברך
לעלה ולקלס למי שעשה לאבותינו ולנו את כל הנסים האלו. lefikhakh anachnu
chayavim lehodot lehalel leshabe'ach lefa'er leromem lehadar levarach le'aleh u'lekales lemi she'asa
la'avoteinu velanu et kol hanisim ha'eilu. Clearly it is not the משנה
Mishna talking, meaning it's not the text of a משנה. Mishna It's
not saying לפיכך lefikhakh you have to say הלל. Hallel. This is
clearly a text of a הגדה Haggadah in the משנה. Mishna So
at some point we transitioned from the משנה Mishna talking as the
משנה Mishnah to the משנה Mishnah giving us the text of the
הגדה, Haggadah, right? If it was just telling us הלכה, Halakha, it
would not have used seven different ways of saying להודות להלל לשבח
לפאר לרומם להדר לעלה. lehodot lehalel leshabe'ach lefa'er leromem lehadar le'aleh. למי
שעשה לאבותינו ולנו? lemi she'asa la'avoteinu velanu? Us? I mean clearly we
now have in the משנה Mishnah a text of the
הגדה, Haggadah, וממות לחיים מעבדות לחירות מיגון לשמחה מאבל ליום טוב מאפילה
לאור גדול ומשעבוד לגאולה ונואמר לפניו הללויה. u'mimavet lechayim me'avdut l'cheirut miyagon
l'simcha me'eivel l'yom tov me'afeila l'or gadol u'mishibud l'geula v'nomar lefanav hallelujah.
And that is an introduction to the הלל Hallel that comes at
the end, right? Remember we said just before, what would we have
to do? He said to Daru, Daru said oh you have to
praise him and thank him, so when you get to experiencing גאולה
Geula and seeing yourself as if you experienced it and that ties
into the Daru story with the slave, if you really feel that
way, what are you חייב chayav to do at this moment? Obviously
you have to break out into song and that ties into the
הלל. Hallel. Dov, what did you want to say?
I would suggest that when רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says שלשה דברים
אלו, shlosha devarim eilu, the three things are, one, פסח מצה מרור,
Pesach Matzah Maror, you have to explain the things. Two, חייב אדם
לראות את עצמו. chayav adam lirot et atzmo. And three, ולהודות
להלל. u'lehodot lehalel.
Oh
that is fascinating.
I don't think I know anyone else who's explained it that way,
but that's a fascinating read. Yes.
Since this gives the point at which you're supposed to recite הלל,
Hallel, and so if you recite in synagogue, you haven't gotten to
that point yet.
Well, the synagogue saying of הלל Hallel probably represents the הלל Hallel
of the הקרבת הפסח. hakravat hapesach. This is the הלל Hallel of
the אכילת הפסח. achilat hapesach. Now I should say by the way,
that the reason there's a question why we don't make הלל Hallel
בליל סדר, beleil seder, there's no ברכה bracha. by הלל Hallel בליל
סדר beleil seder because we normally make a ברכה. bracha And the
best answer is, is because you make a ברכה bracha when you're
doing something more as a ritual and not as a just giving
expression to an inner religious feeling. And if you really have achieved
לפיכך אנחנו חייבים lefikhakh anachnu chayavim and חייב לראות את עצמו, chayav
lirot et atzmo, then it's a natural type of a thing and
it's not formalized as a ritual of a מצוה mitzvah. that you
want to frame it with we're doing it because of a מצוה.
We're not doing it because of a מצוה. If we've really lived
this we're doing it because it's how we feel. What did you
want to say?
There's also the מחלוקת machloket of יום העצמאות Yom Ha'atzmaut where we
say ברכה.
bracha Yeah, but that's not related to this. Okay, so that obviously
is we do the רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, we explain the things,
we do לפיכך, lefikhakh, כל דור ודור חייב אדם לראות את עצמו,
kol dor vador chayav adam lirot et atzmo, so we make it
personal. We've told the story, hopefully you've driven it home, it's become
personal and therefore that leads into the לפיכך lefikhakh and leads into
the הלל Hallel which ends with the גאל ישראל. Ga'al Yisrael. So
or
so let's take a look. עד היכן הוא אומר? ad heikan hu
omer? How far do you say the הלל Hallel for the first
half of the סדר? You're going to finish it at the second
half of the סדר. בית שמאי אומרים עד אם הבנים שמחה Beit
Shammai omerim ad em habanim smeicha ובית הלל אומרים עד חלמיש למעינו
מים. u'Beit Hillel omerim ad chalamish lemayno mayim. I really don't have
an interesting explanation for what this debate is about. You know if
you just take a look at what this is,
right,
so he says the first part, בית הלל Beit Hillel says two,
what's really fascinating is that the second paragraph of הלל Hallel opens
right with בצאת ישראל ממצרים, Betzeit Yisrael miMitzrayim, בית יעקב מעם לועז.
Beit Yaakov me'am lo'ez. So I really have no understanding of בית
שמאי Beit Shammai of why he would not want you to say
the בצאת ישראל ממצרים. Betzeit Yisrael miMitzrayim. Again, unless he feels that
it's בצאת ישראל B'tzeis Yisrael and you're making yourself, you're not making
yourself part of the ישראל. Yisrael. You're talking about other people when
they went out of מצרים, Mitzrayim, and to fully embrace it as
you've experienced it, you just want to do the הללויה, Halleluyah, you
don't want to actually talk about a past event of יציאת מצרים
Yetzias Mitzrayim that would take you out of the immediacy of the
moment. That's the best I can understand. But obviously for בית הלל,
Beis Hillel, it's quite understandable. Now why we break up the הלל
Hallel into two parts, we'll talk about that later. But again, part
of the answer has to do with you want to give expression
to the sense of really try to relive it and give voice
to here's how I feel. The more you have to say the
whole הלל, Hallel, the more it becomes a ritual and less an
immediate personal religious experience. And therefore we want to do a short
version. We'll finish it as a ritual of הלל Hallel later. And
that might be בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, but again, still not to
say the בצאת ישראל B'tzeis Yisrael is strange unless, as I said,
בצאת ישראל B'tzeis Yisrael makes you out of the moment. It's not
your ישראל, Yisrael, it's they when they went out of מצרים.
Mitzrayim. Did he do that or he breaks it so that the
first introductory moment of saying הלל Hallel is גנות gnus and then
the שבח shevach of the גאולה geulah comes after the break?
What do you mean? The first introductory moment is
הללויה... Halleluyah...
No, but the ובקיעי הירדן... u-v'ki'ei ha-Yarden...
Ah, ובקיעי הירדן. u-v'ki'ei ha-Yarden. I don't know. Okay, so anyway let's
finish up. וחותם בגאולה v'chosem b'geulah and you end with גאולה geulah
after the הלל. Hallel. So רבי טרפון אומר, Rabbi Tarfon omer, אשר
גאלנו וגאל את אבותינו ממצרים, asher ge'alanu v'ga'al es avoseinu mi-Mitzrayim, ולא
היה חותם. v'lo hayah chosem. The whole ברכה bracha, would be: ברוך
אתה השם אלקינו מלך העולם אשר גאלנו וגאל את אבותינו ממצרים.
Baruch atah Hashem elokeinu melech ha-olam asher ge'alanu v'ga'al es
avoseinu mi-Mitzrayim. Period. Then you drink it. It's a ברכה bracha on
the past גאולה. geulah. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, כן השם
אלקינו ואלקי אבותינו יגיענו למועדים ולרגלים אחרים הבאים לקראתנו לשלום שמחים בבנין
עירך וששים בעבודתך ונאכל שם מן הזבחים ומן הפסחים kein Hashem elokeinu
v'elokei avoseinu yagi'einu l'moadim u'l'regalim acherim habaim likrasenu l'shaloam s'meichim b'vinyan iracha
v'sasim b'avodasecha v'nochal sham min hazevachim u-min hapesachim that's שבת or whatever
because you have the חגיגה chagigah first and then you'd have
the קרבן פסח korban pesach as פסח נאכל על השובע... pesach ne'echal
al hasova... questions anyway of the order... עד ברוך אתה השם גאל
ישראל. ad Baruch atah Hashem ga'al Yisrael. Okay,
which is our נוסח. nusach. So the first one, רבי טרפון, Rabbi
Tarfon, if it's a short ברכה as we learned, you don't have
a חתימה. chasima. If it's a long ברכה, כן השם, kein Hashem,
then you have to repeat, you have to seal it, you have
to have a coda and you have the חתימה chasima ברוך אתה
השם גאל ישראל. Baruch atah Hashem ga'al Yisrael. So two points to
be made about this. Number one is תוספות and the רשב"ם Rashbam
both say there're not three opinions here, there's two. וחותם בגאולה. v'chosem
b'geulah. What does that גאולה geulah mean? That's the debate of רבי
טרפון Rabbi Tarfon and רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, and that is important
because they point out this phenomenon in the משנה that there's going
to be an earlier line of a משנה that is not explicated
and later תנאים Tannaim debate what the meaning of that earlier line
is. So the earlier line of the משנה is וחותם בגאולה, v'chosem
b'geulah, later comes along רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon and רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva and they debate what that חתימה chasima is. Now it's also
interesting to note that רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, what does he really
add? He didn't just make it longer. כן השם אלקינו kein Hashem
elokeinu points us to future גאולה geulah and to בנין בית המקדש,
binyan Beis Hamikdash, which is very connected to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva,
who by בר כוכבא Bar Kochba was constantly looking for future גאולה,
geulah, the story about the הר הבית Har Habayis that was destroyed,
oh no but this is a promise that it'll be fulfilled. So
how much is the story of the הגדה Haggadah not only a
story of leading up to הר סיני Har Sinai
but also a story of future גאולה geulah is a very interesting
question. And you could certainly understand the importance of that at a
time when we were oppressed to be thinking about that sense of
the future redemption and so on, which is a theme that starts
coming up in the second part of the סדר night. That is
something that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva sees as central. One other point
before we get to the גמרא Gemara. is the חייב לראות את
עצמו, chayav liros es atzmo, see yourself, which is a pretty high
standard. The רמב"ם גרסה girsa is חייב להראות את עצמו. chayav l'haros
es atzmo. You have to demonstrate, you have to present yourself as
if, which is a more reasonable standard. What is it, fake it
'til you make it. So if you can't actually feel it, at
least to go through the motions as if and that hopefully then
it'll internalize to some degree. Okay, let's read a little bit in
the גמרא. אמר רבא: Amar Rava: צריך שיאמר ואותנו הוציא משם. tzarich
she-yomar v'osanu hotzi misham. Since you're saying that God, חייב לראות את
עצמו, chayav liros es atzmo, you have to end by saying like
what's the פסוק... pasuk... ביום ההוא לאמר בעבור זה עשה השם לי
ואותנו הוציא משם, b'yom ha-hu laymor ba'avur zeh asah Hashem li v'osanu
hotzi misham, למען הביא אותנו. l'ma'an havi osanu. You have to have
the end of the ברכה that speaks about us being brought out,
again making it as if you yourself were part of it. אמר
רבא: Amar Rava: מצה צריך להגביה, matzah tzarich l'hagbi'ah, when you do
the פסח מצה מרור, Pesach matzah maror, you lift up the מצה
and you say מצה זו. matzah zu. מרור צריך להגביה, maror tzarich
l'hagbi'ah, you lift that up, a little show and tell. בשר אין
צריך להגביה. basar ein tzarich l'hagbi'ah. You don't lift up the meat.
Presumably the שני תבשילים shnei sevshilin we're talking about. Okay, לא עוד
אלא שנראה כאוכלי קדשים בחוץ. lo od ela she-neireh k'ochlei kodshim bachutz.
If you indicate that this and you talk about this when you're
talking about the פסח, Pesach it looks like you're eating the פסח
and this is the opposite point. Not to have roasted meat, to
have a
roasted lamb, but דווקא, davka, yes, some symbolism of it but you
downplay it. You don't want to look like you're eating קרבנות korbanos
outside.
And I guess unfortunately we will have to end here, we will
pick up tomorrow.
Okay, see you everyone.